# Arch. Peter Wafula Mola

P. O Box 328 - 00517 Nairobi KENYA

Cell phone: +254 796034977, email: wafulapmola@yahoo.com.

# **EXECUTIVE LEADERSHIP**

Broad leadership experience over 34 years of working experience in the building and construction industry in the field of Architecture, of which 5 years working as Principal Architect in Architectural Consultancy in Kenya (Terpi Architects), 6 years were spent working in the position of Principal Architect (Project Management) on a construction site in Botswana, 1 year as Resident Architect on a construction site in Botswana, 5 years heading the Architecture and Buildings Department in Botswana (Kgalagadi District Council) and 6 years as Principal and Senior Architect in Architectural Consultancies in Botswana and 11 years as Architect and Superintending Architect in the Ministry of Public Works and Housing in Kenya.

# **EDUCATIONAL AND PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT**

Bachelor of Architecture Degree, Middle East Technical University, Ankara, Turkey

### PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS

1993 **Registered Architect** – Board of Registration of Architects and Quantity Surveyors (BORAQS) of Kenya, Architects Chapter in accordance with the Architects and Quantity Surveyors Act (Cap 525) of the Laws of Kenya: Reg. No. A708.

# LEADERSHIP EXPERIENCE

Principal Architect, Terpi Architects (Nairobi)	2018 to date
Principal Architect, Letsididi and Associates, Architects (Botswana)	2016 to 2017
Principal Architect, A J Consult (Botswana)	2008 to 2016
Senior Architect, Tectura International (Botswana)	2007 to 2008
Senior Architect, Dalgleish Lindsay Group (Botswana)	2006 to 2007
Principal Architect, Kgalagadi District Council (Botswana)	2003 to 2005
Senior Architect, Kgalagadi District Council (Botswana)	2000 to 2003
Superintending Architect, Ministry of Roads & Public Works (Kenya)	1999 to 2000
Architect I, Ministry of Roads & Public Works (Kenya)	1994 to 1999
Architect II, Ministry of Roads & Public Works (Kenya)	1989 to 1994

#### **Noted Accomplishment**

- As Principal Architect (Terpi Architects). I performed duties of Principal Architect for pre and post contract management of projects including tendering, design, documentation, cost control, preparation of payment certificates, and coordination of consultants from related disciplines, supervision of construction of projects, meetings and office supervision.
- As Principal Architect (A J Consult), I was attached to contractor for a duration of 6 years and carried out duties of project manager on behalf of the contractor in the construction of a senior secondary school project. I was in charge of coordinating the activities on the construction site between contractor and the subcontractors, quality control, safety health and environment, maintenance of schedules and timelines and liaising with the design consultants and the client.

For the rest of the duration I performed duties of Principal Architect for pre and post contract management of projects including tendering, design, documentation, cost control, preparation of payment certificates, and coordination of consultants from related disciplines, supervision of construction of projects, meetings and office supervision.

- As senior Architect (Tectura International), performed the duties of resident architect in the construction of a senior secondary school. I was in charge of coordinating the activities of the associated resident consultants' team, liaising between the contractor and the resident consultants, overseeing the construction activities, quality control, safety health and environment, raising of payment certificates and ensuring that the necessary schedules and timelines are adhered to.
- As Principal Architect (Kgalagadi District Council), was Head of Department of the Architecture and Building Department. I oversaw the day to day operations of the department including supervising and coordinating the activities of the staff in the department, overseeing the implementation of the planned Council architectural projects, maintenance works for council buildings and residential houses and, drawing up plans and activities for the department and budgeting.

\_\_\_\_\_

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# **Principal Architect**

Terpi Architects, Kenya: 2018 to Date

### **Key Responsibilities**

- Perform duties of Principal Architect for Pre and Post Contract Management of projects
  - Procurement of projects through tendering and direct commissions
  - Design, documentation, cost control tendering and post contract management of projects
  - Preparation of payment certificates
  - Coordination of consultants from related disciplines
  - Supervision of construction of projects
  - Meetings and office supervision

Letsididi & Associates, Architects (Pty) Ltd, Botswana: 2016 to 2017

### **Key Responsibilities**

- Perform duties of Principal Architect for Pre and Post Contract Management of projects
  - Procurement of projects through tendering and direct commissions
  - Design, documentation, cost control tendering and post contract management of projects
  - Preparation of payment certificates
  - Coordination of consultants from related disciplines
  - Supervision of construction of projects
  - Meetings and office supervision

# **Principal Architect**

A J Consult (Pty) Ltd, Botswana: 2008 to 2016

### **Key Responsibilities**

- Perform duties of Principal Architect for Pre and Post Contract Management of projects
  - Procurement of projects through tendering and direct commissions
  - Design, documentation, cost control tendering and post contract management of projects
  - Preparation of payment certificates
  - Coordination of consultants from related disciplines
  - Supervision of construction of projects
  - Meetings and office supervision

# **Senior Architect**

Tectura International (Pty) Ltd, Botswana: 2007 to 2008

# **Key Responsibilities**

- Resident Architect on the construction of a Senior Secondary School Project at Goodhope, a fast track project worth P340Million implemented by DBES on behalf of the Ministry of Education.
  - Coordination of activities of the Resident Staff comprising of Civil/Structural Engineers, Quantity Surveyor, Electrical/Mechanical Engineers and Clerks of Works.
  - Coordination of activates on the site including quality control, preparation of payment certificates, cost estimates, construction details, as built drawings and advise client on any alterations required and obtain authorization for the changes.

# **Senior Architect**

Dalgleish Lindsay Group (Pty) Ltd, Botswana: 2006 to 2007

# **Key Responsibilities**

- Assigned to the Project Management Team under BCHOD Consulting Engineers who were the Project Managers of the Primary School Facilities Backlog Eradication Project whose combined value was over P350Million that was implemented by the Ministry of Local Government.
  - To review Client's brief, standardization designs for the required facilities
  - To determine the magnitude of the backlog affecting all primary schools in Botswana
  - To draw up Terms of Reference for consultants (Architects, Civil/Structural Engineers, Electrical Engineers, Mechanical Engineers and Quantity Surveyors to implement projects in conjunction with the Client.
  - To coordinate the flow of information between the Ministry of Local Government and the consultants engaged to manage the projects.
  - To oversee the tendering and the evaluation process

- To manage the implementation of the projects located on various sites within Botswana on behalf of the Client
- To prepare and maintain a master cost plan and advise Client on any alterations required and obtain necessary authorization for the changes
- To oversee the implementation of the projects.

#### **Principal Architect:** 2003 to 2005

#### **Senior Architect:** 2000 to 2003

# Ministry of Local Government - Kgalagadi District Council, Botswana

### **Key Responsibilities**

- To ensure that all pre and post contract programmes are achieved as planned in terms of cost, duration and quality. Head of Department representing the Council in the implementation of all Council projects.
  - Primary health facilities comprising of clinics (out-patient department, maternity ward, maternal health clinic & public ablution) rural health posts, doctors and nurses houses and associated external works comprising of access roads, fencing, paving, external lighting, storm water drainage, soil and waste water drainage, landscaping, etc.).
  - Primary education facilities comprising of classroom blocks, school kitchens, dining halls, administration blocks, teachers' houses, school ablutions and associated external works.
  - Social and community development projects comprising of Remote Area Dwellers (RADS) hostels, carpentry and leather workshops, community halls, mechanical workshops and local authority staff houses and associated external works as above.
  - Mechanical transport Workshop comprising of Workshop building, offices, auxiliary facilities, parking and external works.
  - Water unit workshops comprising of workshop buildings, offices, auxiliary facilities and external works.
  - Routine and cyclic maintenance works of all the above facilities comprising of building condition assessments, preparing dilapidation schedules and tender documents for the maintenance works.

# **Superintending Architect**

1999 to 2000

1989 to 1994

Architect I 1994 to 1999 Architect II

# Ministry of Public Works, Kenya

# **Key Responsibilities**

Perform duties for Pre and post contract management of projects including design, documentation, cost control, preparation of payment certificates, coordination of consultants form relevant disciplines, meetings supervision of construction and office supervision.

Pro	Projects		
P	Projects handled in Kenya		
1	Residential Flats, Ngong		
2	Residential House, Nyahururu		
3	5No. Maisonettes, Juja		
4	Residential House, Malaba		

5.	Residential House, Mavoko Town			
Dr	ojects handled in Botswana			
_	Primary School Facilities			
1.	Teachers, quarters, classrooms, kitchens and ablution facilities in various villages within Kgalagadi			
	District			
RAI	RADS hostel			
1.	Dormitories, Dining Hall, Games room, and Matrons house at Hunhukwe			
Wa	ter Unit Facilities			
1.	Offices and Workshop at Tsabong			
2.	Offices at Bokspits and Kang			
Clir	Clinic Facilities			
1.	Nurses quarters in various villages within Kgalagadi District			
2.	New clinic – Outpatient, Maternity and MCH clinic at Kang			
3.	New clinic – Outpatient clinic at Tsabong.			
4.	New clinic – Maternity clinic at Werda.			
5.	Council, District and Tribal Administration Housing in various villages within the Kgalagadi District.			
Me	Mechanical Transport Workshop			
1.	New Mechanical Workshop, Offices and auxiliary facilities at Tsabong. Location: Botswana.			
Sen	ior Secondary School at Goodhope			
1.	Administration block, Classroom blocks, Science laboratories, Multi-Purpose Hall, Ablution blocks,			
	Kitchen & Dining Block, Hostel Block, Associated external works, Sports fields.			
Sen	ior Secondary School at Shakawe			
1.	Administration block, Classroom blocks, Science laboratories,			
	Multi-Purpose Hall, Ablution blocks, Kitchen & Dining Block, Hostel Block, Associated external works,			
	Sports fields.			
_	Residential and Commercial			
1.	Several Residential Houses			
2.	Office Block			
Pro	ojects Handled – Ministry of Roads & Public Works, Kenya			
1.	Office Block – Alterations to Roof at Harambee House, Nairobi			
2.	Proposed N.Y.S. Engineering Institute Classroom facilities, Nairobi.			
3.	NYS Naivasha, Phase III – Officer's mess, Hostels, Dining Halls, Residential Houses and other auxiliary			
	facilities at Naivasha			
4.	Kapenguria Divisional Police Headquarters – Office block, residentioal houses and other auxiliary			
+	facilities at Kapenguria.			
5.	Nandi District Headquarters – Office block for the District Headquarters at Kapsabet.			
6.	Kitale Divisional Police Headquarters – Office block, Residential Houses and other auxiliary facilities at			
-	Kitale.			
7.	Uasin Gishu District Headquarters – Office block for the District Headquarters at Eldoret.			
8.	New Nyanza Provincial Headquarters – Office Block at Kisumu.			
9.	Kapsabet Divisional Police Headquarters – Office block, Residential houses and other auxiliary facilities at Kapsabet.			
10.	National Youth Service, Naivasha Phase IV – Officer's Mess, Hostels, Dining Halls, Residential Houses			
	and other auxiliary facilities at Naivasha.			
11.	Nairobi West Park Housing at Langata – 595No. Residential houses, Nursery School, Commercial			
	complex and auxiliary facilities at Nairobi.			
12.	Proposed Government Chemist – Design of Office and Laboratory facilities Nairobi.			

# **COMPUTER SOFTWARE PROFICIENCY**

- AutoCAD
- ArchiCAD
- MicroSoft Office Word, Excel and Project

# Referees

Eng. ANTHONY J. MATILYA
QS M.N. OGAMA
SUSAN OTIENO
P.O. Box 3909
P.O. Box 50972 00100
Executive Director
ActionAid International
Botswana
Kenya
P.O. Box 12045 – 00100

Nairobi

Mobile No. +267 717675144 Mobile No. 0722818925 Mobile No. 0722688439

matilyaaj@gmail.com mathiasogama@yahoo.com susan.otieno@actionaid.org